<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of loue Instructing all men to vnite and ioyne themselues in hearty loue, and Christian charitie with one another. Preached at Folkestone, a maior towne in Kent. By Francis Rogers, Batchelor in Diuinity; and sometimes fellow of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Rogers, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112048</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847307</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847307</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1581:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of loue Instructing all men to vnite and ioyne themselues in hearty loue, and Christian charitie with one another. Preached at Folkestone, a maior towne in Kent. By Francis Rogers, Batchelor in Diuinity; and sometimes fellow of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for George Norton, dwelling neare Temple-barre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12337:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12337:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF <hi>LOVE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſtructing all men to vnite and <hi>ioyne themſelues in hearty Loue, and</hi> Chriſtian Charitie one with another.</p>
            <p>Preached at <hi>Folkeſtone,</hi> a Maior <hi>Towne in Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY FRANCIS ROGERS, Batchelor in Diuinity; and ſometimes fellow of Trinitie Colledge in CAMBRIDGE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOHN 13.35.</hi>
               </bibl> By this ſhall all men know if yee be my Diſciples, if yee Loue one another.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROMANES 16.17.</hi>
               </bibl> Now I beſeech you brethren, marke them diligently which cauſe diuiſion and offences, and auoid them.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T.S.</hi> for <hi>George Norton,</hi> dwelling neare Temple-barre. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12337:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12337:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorſhipfull, his very louing <hi>Mother,</hi> ANNE ROGERS Widow, within the precinct of <hi>Chriſtes Church</hi> CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERBVRY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Husbandman doth not plant his Tree, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, Dongue it, Lop it, Prune it, to the end that when the time of bearing Fruit is come, it ſhould be like the Fig-Tree, to bring foorth Leaues and no Fruit; but rather that it ſhould be like vnto the Vine-tree which doth bring forth fruit in cluſters, and in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance: euen ſo man, which is <hi>planta inuerſa,</hi> a Tree, with his roote vpward, is not nouriſhed in the wombe of his Mother for the ſpace of fortie weekes together, and after he is borne into the world, hee is not ſuckled, fed, ſwadled, and tended by Mothers naturall care,
<pb facs="tcp:12337:3"/>
and tender affection, to that end, that when hee is ripe in yeeres hee ſhould proue like <hi>Abſalon,</hi> a ſtubborne and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient childe, but rather to be like our Sauiour CHRIST, who was obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to his Father and Mother in all things, that ſo he may be a ioy vnto his Father, and make glad the heart of his Mother.</p>
            <p>And howſoeuer <hi>Alexander</hi> the great propoundeth it as a great queſtion, whether a man be more beholding to his Father which begetteth him, or to his Maſter which teacheth him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the one is occaſion of his being, the other of his well-being: yet the Lawes of God and Nature tell vs that all reuerent reſpect, &amp; dutifull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is to be caried to our Father which begat vs, &amp; to our Mother which bare vs: almighty God hauing promiſed in the fift Commandement a ſpecial bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of long life vpon earth to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient childe. Wherefore as when the Grecians in a great ſolemnitie did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to <hi>Philip</hi> king of <hi>Macedon</hi> many goodly gifts; a poore Painter ſtepped in
<pb facs="tcp:12337:3"/>
among the reſt, and offred vp the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit of himſelfe in a Table, beſides which, were purtrayed out many Iewels, and Pearles, &amp; Rings, ouer each where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was inſcribed, <hi>Vellem &amp; hoc:</hi> I would I were able to giue ſuch gifts as theſe. Euen ſo my ſelfe, hauing at this time occaſion, by importunitie of friends, to expoſe theſe my ſimple labours of that poore Talent wherewith God hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued mee, to the worlds view (<hi>vtinam foeliciter,</hi> God giue it good ſucceſſe) haue thought it my duetie to preſent vnto your ſelfe (moſt deare Mother) theſe my firſt, though vnworthy endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, vnfainedly proteſting, that if there be any thing wherein I may ſhew my obedience, and bring comfort to your olde age, <hi>Vellem &amp; hoc,</hi> I deſire of God that I may performe it. In the meane time let me entreate this fauour at your hands, that as <hi>Lewis</hi> the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth King of <hi>France,</hi> preſented with a great roote by one of his poore ſubiects, perceiuing that it came from an hearty affection, tooke it in good part, and loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it vp in his Treaſurie among his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt
<pb facs="tcp:12337:4"/>
Iewels: ſo let mee beſeech you to accept this ſimple preſent, as an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teſtimonie of my true hearty loue, and Filiall reuerence to you, my moſt louing and naturall Mother, and ſo I humbly take my leaue; earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating Almighty God to giue you in this life peace of conſcience, which is a continuall feaſt; and at the houre of your death to bring your gray haires with ioy vnto the graue; and after this miſerable life is ended, to giue you peace of ſoule and body for euermore, in his bleſſed Kingdome of Heauen: which God the Father graunt for his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your dutifull and obedient Sonne <hi>vnto his power,</hi> FRANCIS ROGERS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12337:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith very well, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet neſcio quid latentis energiae viua vox, &amp; in aures diſcipuli de authoris ore transfuſa fortius ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat:</hi> the liuely voyce of man, ſpeaking hath ſome eſpeciall ſecret operation in the minde, and doth ſend a more ſtrong ſound into the eares of the hearer In which reſpect, I perſwade my ſelfe this Sermon will prooue like vnto Tapeſtry wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> which ſeemeth faire farre off, but when yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neere vnto it, you may diſcerne the courſeneſſe of the threed; for as Philoſophy tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, the eare is a farre more dull iudge then the eye; and reaſon teacheth vs, that we cannot ſo truely diſcerne of things which ſuddenly paſſe away, as of obiects which are ſtill permanent.</p>
            <p>Therefore as alwayes, ſo now eſpecially, I did deſire to imitate <hi>Plato</hi> the Diuine Philoſopher, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Maluit aliena verecunde diſcere, quam ſua impudenter ingerere:</hi> Hee had rather learne of others with modeſtie, then impudently make ſhew of his owne knowledge. Yet the importunitie of my fellow-brethren and Miniſters, then preſent, was ſuch, as my caſe did reſemble the ſeruants of King <hi>Eglon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 3.25.</note> they tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at the doore till they were aſhamed: ſo I denied them ſo long as I was aſhamed to deny them any more. Wherefore now I preſent this Sermon vnto thee (gentle Reader) accept it
<pb facs="tcp:12337:5"/>
kindely, read it patiently, cenſure it charitably, and practiſe it diligently. If thou reapeſt any good thereby, giue the glory to him who is the Author and giuer of euery good gift: onely thus much I aduertiſe thee: <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher in his bookes doth often refell the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Maſter <hi>Plato,</hi> and he neuer doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his ſo doing, but onely in his Ethickes; the reaſon whereof is giuen, that hee being in thoſe bookes to giue precepts of good manners vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, would not himſelfe ſeeme ſo much to tranſgreſſe the bounds of modeſtie &amp; good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as once publikely to write againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter which taught him, and his Tutor which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed him, without good reaſon and lawfull excuſe. Euen ſo remember (good Reader) that when thou doeſt reade this Sermon, thou doeſt read a Treatiſe of <hi>LOVE,</hi> then do not while thou art reading of loue, ſo farre degenerate from the nature of loue, and bond of Chriſtian Charitie, as once to giue it an harſh cenſure, and vncharitable conſtruction: <hi>humanum eſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare,</hi> to erre, and be deceiued, is proper to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailtie: <hi>ergo pietatis eſt ignoſcere, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitatis non agnoſcere;</hi> therefore pietie teacheth thee to forgiue the faults, &amp; humanitie biddeth thee not to acknowledge the faults: And thus I commit thee to the protection of the moſt high God. From <hi>Alkham</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Kent,</hi> this <hi>10.</hi> of <hi>February. 1613.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>FRANCIS ROGERS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12337:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON OF LOVE: Inſtructing all men to vnite and ioyne themſelues in harty Loue and Chriſtian Charitie, <hi>one with another.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTHEVV 22.39.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith of the whole Booke of <hi>Iob,</hi> may moſt truely be verified of this ſaying of our Sauiour: namely, <hi>Singula in eo verba plena ſunt ſenſibus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiero. Paul.</note> that is, Euery word is a full ſentence, affording large ſcope, and ample matter for to entreate of: but that I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12337:6"/>
may the better confine my ſelfe vnto the time allotted for this buſineſſe, obſerue three things: firſt, a commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue:</hi> ſecondly, the obiect vvhom wee muſt loue, <hi>thy neighbour:</hi> thirdly, the meane how farre this loue muſt be extended, <hi>as thy ſelfe.</hi> Of the precept.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt loue.]</hi> The Morall Law of God, contained in the ten Commandements, is diuided into two Tables: the firſt ſetteth forth our duty vnto God, wherein nothing elſe is required at our hands but Loue; ſo ſaith our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.38.</note> 
               <hi>The firſt and greateſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is this, Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy ſoule, and with all thy minde:</hi> where we learne our loue to God muſt be like vnto death; for there is no earthly liuing creature, ſo ſtrong, ſo weake, ſo rich, ſo poore, ſo olde, ſo young, ſo noble, ſo ignoble, of what condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, but Death doth ouer-come all: euen ſo, though wee may loue Wife, Children, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Mother, Brother, Siſter, Kinsfolke, Friends, Honors, goods, and our owne liues, yet the loue of GOD muſt ſurpaſſe them all, or elſe wee are not worthy of God ſaith our Sauiour. The ſecond Table containeth our dutie towards our Neighbour, and therein likewiſe is nothing elſe required at our hands but Loue;<note place="margin">Mat. 10.37.</note> ſo ſaith my Text, <hi>The ſecond is like vnto this, thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12337:6"/>
ſelfe.</hi> So that as Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 56.</note> ſpeaking of Humilitie, ſaith; the firſt vertue in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, is Humilitie; the ſecond, Humilitie; the third, Humilitie; and ſo often as you vvill aske mee, I will anſwere nothing but Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: not becauſe there are no other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts in the Bible, but becauſe vnleſſe Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie goe before all other vertues, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all other vertues, and follow after euery vertue, Pride will deflowre our holieſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In like manner S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſpeake of Loue, ſaying, that the firſt vertue in a Chriſtian, is Loue; the ſecond, is Loue; the third, yea, all required in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is nothing elſe but Loue: therefore he ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Though I ſpeake with the tongue of men and Angels, and haue not Loue, I am as ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding braſſe, and a tinckling Cymball.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Though I had the gift of Prophecie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 2.</note> 
               <hi>and knew all ſecrets, and all knowledge; yea, if I had all Faith, ſo that I could remoue mountaines, and had not Loue, I were nothing.</hi> And againe, <hi>Though I feede the poore with all my goods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> 
               <hi>and though I giue my body to be burned, and haue not Loue, it profiteth mee nothing.</hi> Hence ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſo many commendations of Loue in the Scripture; as, <hi>Loue enuyeth not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>it ſuffereth all things, it beleeueth all things, it hopeth all things, it endureth all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 2.8.</note> It is <hi>the bond of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the Royall Law: the great commandement:</hi> It is <hi>Chriſts owne precept:</hi> yea,<note place="margin">Iohn 15.12.</note> God himſelfe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12337:7"/>
is tearmed by the name of Loue, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.8. Hence the ancient Writers made ſo many exhortations to loue, and wrote ſo many commendations of Loue. Loue (ſaith <hi>Philo Iudaeus</hi>) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, a ſhort word, but yet it containeth much matter to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of:<note place="margin">Mat. 13.31.</note> like the graine of Muſtard-ſeede, <hi>the leaſt of all other, yet groweth ſo bigge as the Fowles of the ayre build their neſts in the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.9.</note> ſo is Loue <hi>the abridgement of the whole Law:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>the end of the Commandements: the fulfilling of the whole Law:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.10.</note> Inſomuch as <hi>Clement Alexandrinus</hi> calleth a louing man, a God: <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> being asked what was the beſt thing in the world, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie, Peace</hi> and <hi>Concord:</hi> and being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the worſt thing, anſwered, <hi>Hatred, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> and <hi>Contention:</hi> this is illuſtrated by a Similitude.</p>
            <p>As maine Ocean Seas, and deepe Riuers in themſelues are fit for ſhips to ſaile in, and to hinder the paſſage of enemies into the Country which they enuiron; but let them be cut into narrow channels and ſmall gutters, then they are vnfit for eyther. Euen ſo where there is loue and amitie, there all things proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: by concord ſmall things become great, but where is diſcord and ſtrife, there nothing flouriſheth, for by diſſention great things become ſmall;<note place="margin">Luke 11.2.</note> yea, nothing at all. For King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes (ſaith our Sauiour) diuided among
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12337:7"/>
themſelues cannot endure. Though God had often foretolde of the miſerable deſtruction of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſephus de bell. Iudae.</note> which was performed by the Romanes, yet nothing did worke their ſo ſpeedy and lamentable ruine as their owne diſſentions and ciuill warres within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: ſee this likewiſe verified in the aeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomicall gouernment.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is vvorthy noting that <hi>Silu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> hauing foureſcore ſonnes, ſeeing them at diſcord among themſelues, tyed vp a great Faggot of ſtickes together, and gaue to each ſonne a piece of the cord which tyed them, and bad them all aſſaye to breake the Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, vvhich vvhen they had long endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red they could not effect; vvhereupon the old man looſed the Faggot and gaue to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſonne one ſingle ſticke, vvhich euery one could eaſily breake in ſunder: euen ſo, while Chriſtians and brethren vnite themſelues in Loue and Charitie, ſo long it is hard for them to be ouerthrowne; but vvhen once they are at hatred within themſelues, then the deuill eaſily ouercommeth them, for he goeth vp and downe like a roaring Lyon ſeeking vvhom he may deuoure: vvhere the Greeke is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quem,</hi> vvho in the ſingular number catching them one by one, not <hi>quos</hi> in the plurall number, vvhen they goe in couples. Obſerue likewiſe how diſcord in the members ouerthrow the priuate body
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12337:8"/>
of euery particular man; therefore it is a pretty fable in <hi>Aeſope</hi> that at a certaine time the members in the body fell at diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vvith the belly; the hand vvould reach it no meate, the foote vvould goe for no meat, in the end all the whole body vvaxed ſo feeble as it was ready to periſh; then the hand would reach meat, the foot fetch meat, the mouth chawe meat; but alas, it was too late to ſhut the doore after the Steed vvas ſtolne, for the belly was ſo faint and weake as it was able to receiue no meate, and ſo the vvhole body was conſumed, and as diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ouerthroweth kingdomes, priuate fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, the ſoules and bodies of men; euen ſo it doth wholy conſume the wealth and eſtates of men, as is ſeene in the lame man and the blinde man, of which, one for want of lims vvas not able to goe, the other for want of eyes could not ſee to goe, vntill at laſt they agreed together that the blinde man ſhould carry the lame man, &amp; the lame man ſhould guide the blinde man: thus they went on well and quietly, vntill the lame man had eſpied an Oyſter, then they fell at diſſention to whom it did belong; the lame man chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged it, becauſe he eſpyed it out, the blinde man ſayd it was his, becauſe his legs did fetch it; to be ſhort, in the end they determined to be iudged by the next man they met: this man being a Lawyer, made an equall diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12337:8"/>
hee gaue each of them a ſhell, and kept the meate to himſelfe: and euen ſo goe on in ſuites and iarres at laſt ye vvill find the Lawyer to be like the Butlers boxe at Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, whoſoeuer is a looſer that is a gainer.</p>
            <p>Wee which liue in this latter age of the vvorld haue beene long time the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> but vvee could neuer yet take foorth our leſſon ſo farre foorth as Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> or Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> wee haue learned of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to beleeue well, but not of Saint of <hi>Iames</hi> to bring forth good workes which are the fruits of faith: vvee haue learned of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to feede Chriſts flocke, and the people to be fed of the ſhepheard, but neither ſhepheard nor ſheepe, Miniſter nor people, haue learned of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to loue one another, who as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was the beloued of Chriſt, ſo are his Epiſtles filled with words of loue, and drops of fatherly affection, as Babes, little Babes, Children, little children, Beloued, deerely beloued. We reade of countries and Ilands which doe not nouriſh any vile or poyſon ſome creatures, but neuer can we reade of a common-wealth wherein liued men whoſe hearts were voyde of enuy, hatred and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.<note place="margin">Actes 2.3.</note> In the Actes of the Apoſtles there is mention made of clouen tongues, but neuer can we finde any clouen hearts, hearts diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſunder; wherefore as euer, ſo eſpecially
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12337:9"/>
now in theſe laſt dayes had we need to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort to loue; for as the vvorld waxeth old, ſo men in the world waxe old; and as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of old men goe ſtooping downeward, ſo the ſoules of men in this age goe groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to earthly poſſeſſions, not minding heauenly inheritances, and as the bodies in olde age vvaxe cold and want the heate of nature, ſo the ſoules of men in this age waxe cold and want the heate of charitie: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if euer then now had this leſſon of Loue need to be enforced, not particularly to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters onely, leaſt then Lay-men ſay, <hi>quod ſupra nos nihil ad nos</hi> (that is) vvhat is aboue vs pertaineth not to vs: nor to the Lay-men onely, leaſt the Clergy ſay, <hi>id populus curet,</hi> that is, let Lay-men Loue, let vs diſagree: but it is generally to be enforced vnto all, of what ſort or condition ſoeuer he be.</p>
            <p>Read the Scripture, you ſhall find how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten loue is commanded; now no man wil of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten demaund that thing which is not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto him, therefore we muſt loue one another becauſe loue is ſo pleaſing vnto GOD, as appeareth by Gods often requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring loue of vs: the Wife which loueth her husband will fit her ſelfe to his humour, ſhe will do that which he delighteth in: We, the Church, are the ſpouſe of Chriſt, hee is our husband, therefore if we truely loue him, we muſt entertaine hearty loue one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12337:9"/>
which is moſt pleaſing vnto God;<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.</note> for loue is likened vnto precious oyntment, which powred foorth, maketh a ſvveet ſauour ouer all the roome: ſo is loue a ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice in the noſtrils of God;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33.</note> hee calling himſelfe the God of Loue, ſaying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that hee hateth him which rayſeth vp contentions among brethren; but in <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticus</hi> Chap. 25. <hi>Three things reioyce mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>and by them am I beautified before God and men, the vnitie of brethren, the loue of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, a man and wife that agree together.</hi> This is ſeene in that <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man after Gods owne heart, muſt not builde an houſe to God: and why? becauſe his hands had beene embrued with blood:<note place="margin">3 Reg. 5.</note> but <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne a king vvhich raigned in peace, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to builde a Temple to God. And IESVS CHRIST vvhich was borne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world to make peace betweene God and man, was borne vnder <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> at that time, when the vvhole vvorld was at peace; therefore ſeeke peace and enſue it, follow after loue, pray with Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> on the <hi>Canticles, Domine pacem volo, pacem cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio &amp; nihil amplius: O Lord I deſire peace, I ſeeke peace and nothing elſe.</hi> Wherefore, doth thy brother offend thee put it vp? refer him to God, who will reuenge thee. <hi>Veterem iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam ferendo vitabis nouam:</hi> By ſuffering an olde iniury, thou ſhalt eſchew a new wrong,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12337:10"/>
as wee ſee in a brawling Curre, if hee barke at thee, and thou ride on, and not regard it, the dogge will be quiet; but if thou offer to chide him, to ſtrike at him, or to hurt him, then hee flyeth at thee more furiouſly then at the beginning.</p>
            <p>A coale of fire let alone will out and dye of it ſelfe, but blow it, and it will burne afreſh and as hot as before: ſo wrongs and iniuries let alone, will in time dye and be forgotten, but if they be repeated, and often rehearſed, they will increaſe.</p>
            <p>I, but thou wilt ſay, for my owne part, I can be contented to liue in peace, but my neighbour is alwayes beginning with mee, and offering me wrong firſt; what ſhould I doe in ſuch a caſe? <hi>Tread on a worme, and it will trune againe.</hi> To this I anſwere: Know what the Heathen Orator ſaith; <hi>Nulla laus eſt ibi eſſe integrum vbi nemo eſt qui aut velit, aut conetur corrumpere:</hi> It is no commendations to be an honeſt man when thou canſt not tell how to be diſhoneſt: for example, What credit is it for a man to ſay he neuer did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultery, when as hee neuer came into company where Women were? What glory is it for a man to be neuer drunken, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be in place where hee can drinke wine or ſtrong Beere, but onely water? So what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation is it to liue in loue &amp; peace, when as no neighbour thou haſt doth offer thee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12337:10"/>
any wrong or iniury. Wherefore hee which offereth thee wrong, giueth thee occaſion of patience, not of anger and reuenge; ſo that euery one ſhould ſay of him which offereth wrong, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of the curſing of <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei; Suffer him to curſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.</note> 
               <hi>for the Lord hath bidden him; it may be the Lord will looke on mine affliction, and doe me good for his curſing this day:</hi> ſo put vp wrong, referre all to God. Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith well, <hi>Quid gloriae eſt illis facere quod fecit Iudas? quid ignominiae eſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis pati quod paſſus eſt Chriſtus?</hi> What glory is it for a man to offer wrong? <hi>Iudas</hi> did the like to Chriſt: and what ſhame is it for vs to ſuffer wrong for Chriſts ſake, who before hath endured much more for our ſakes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Socrates</hi> the wiſe Philoſopher walking in the ſtreetes, pulled off his hat to one whom hee met, which man vnciuilely paſſed by, and left <hi>Socrates</hi> vnſaluted: whereupon one ſaid vnto <hi>Socrates,</hi> Why are you not angry with that vnmannerly companion? To whom <hi>Socrates</hi> replyed, If I had met one with a crooked backe, and which had a body more deformed then my ſelfe, ſhould I be angry with him? To whom the other anſwered, No truely: and then much leſſe haue I cauſe to be diſpleaſed with one that hath a vvorſe minde then I, ſaid the the Philoſopher. Euen ſo, to make ſome application to vs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: Hath thy neighbour done thee iniurie?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12337:11"/>
Surely this proceedeth out of his Soules in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, and therefore be not offended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath a worſe Soule then thy ſelfe: for indeede in ſtead of hurting him againe, thou haſt more neede to pitty him, and to pray for him.</p>
            <p>I, but thou wilt peraduenture ſay, The of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences are not ſmall and ordinary, but great and haynous, ſuch as fleſh and bloud cannot endure.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.50.</note> Alas beloued, <hi>Fleſh and bloud ſhall neuer enter into the Kingdome of Heauen, but he which is borne of water and the Spirit:</hi> and know thus much that the greateſt iniuries offered vnto thee are not comparable to the leaſt ſinne thou committeſt againſt GOD: for the greater the obiect offended, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the ſinne committed. Offer to kill an ordinary man, and not effect it, thou haſt but a ſmall puniſhment; but offer to kill the King, and thou art puniſhed in the higheſt degree: thus you ſee how one and the ſelfe-ſame ſinne is greater and leſſer in regard of the obiect offended; now then almighty God being infinite and eternall, the leaſt ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, deſerueth infinite and eternall puniſhment. How then canſt thou hope for pardon from God for thy great ſins againſt him, when thou wilt not forgiue thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour his ſmall ſinnes againſt thee, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon?<note place="margin">Mat. 18.25.</note> as our Sauiour ſetteth forth at large in the Parable of the vnthankfull Seruant, who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12337:11"/>
hauing to himſelfe forgiuen tenne thouſand Talents, would not forgiue his fellow-ſeruant one hundred pence: this Maſter is God, this Seruant to vvhom tenne thouſand Talents are remitted, is euery Chriſtian which hath his ſins waſhed away in the bloud of Chriſt: theſe hundred pence of the fellow-ſeruant, are thoſe ſmall ſinnes which one brother of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth to another. A Talent was then two hundred pounds, then what difference is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt twenty hundred thouſand pounds, and one hundred pence, ſo much difference and more is there betweene our ſinnes to GOD, and our Brothers to vs.</p>
            <p>O then for ſhame good Chriſtian ſpeake not of the greatneſſe of thy wrongs, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pray ſo much more earneſtly to God, and ſay with our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Luke 22.34.</note> 
               <hi>Father forgiue them, they know not what they doe:</hi> And with the bleſſed Martyr Saint <hi>Steuen,</hi> cry,<note place="margin">Acts 7.60.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord lay not their ſinnes vnto their charge.</hi> Imitate Almighty God, who is quicke to ſhew mercy, as wee ſee in the Prodigall Sonne,<note place="margin">Luke 15.20.</note> to vvhom hee ranne forth ſpeedily, and with all haſte embraced him: but God is ſlow to anger and reuenge; for when hee came to puniſh <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, hee came not running,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.8.</note> but walking; and that not in the heate of the day, but in the coole of the euening: euen ſo, be thou ſwift to forgiue thine enemie. <hi>Let not the Sunne goe downe vpon thy wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.26.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12337:12"/>
but be ſlow to anger and reuenge: for, <hi>hee which is angry with his Brother vnaduiſedly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be culpable of Iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I, but thou wilt yet ſay, I can be contented to liue in peace, to forgiue great wrongs, but I am often wronged, and ſtill iniured, I can neuer liue in quiet. Know thus much my beloued,<note place="margin">Iames 3.2. Pſal. 19.12.</note> that not in one or two things, but in many things wee all ſinne againſt God: and who is hee which knoweth all his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities?<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> Had not euery one neede to pray with <hi>Dauid, Lord clenſe me from my ſecret ſinnes?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 11.4.</note> Doth not our Sauiour teach vs daily to pray, <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes?</hi> And alſo daily to practiſe forgiueneſſe to our brother ſinne he not ſeauen times,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.22.</note> but ſeauenty times ſeauen times in one day. Conſult not therefore with fleſh and bloud, but ſubmit thy ſelfe to Gods Law, which telleth thee, that <hi>the greateſt Commandement is to loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy ſoule, and with all thy minde, and that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is like vnto this, Thou ſhalt loue thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore be not a Chriſtian in ſhew, but in deedes, imitate thy Sauiour Ieſus, who doth not onely not hate his enemies, but beſtoweth many benefits vpon them, as, his Sunne ſhineth vpon the iuſt and vniuſt, his raine falleth vpon the good and bad: ſo do not onely not reuenge thee on thy enemie,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12337:12"/>
but loue him, doe him good, and pray for him: and reaſon good; for if GOD the Creator ſpareth his Creature, much more muſt thou ſpare thy Fellow-Creature: if GOD, the Lord of all, doe forgiue his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, then muſt thou forgiue thy Fellow-ſeruants, Wherefore embrace loue with all men, <hi>If thine enemy be hungry, feede him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.22.</note> 
               <hi>if hee be thirſty, giue him drinke; if hee be naked, clothe him: for in ſo doing thou ſhalt heape coales of fire vpon his head:</hi> that is, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De doct. Chriſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> thou ſhalt ſtirre vp in thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie the burning zeale and ſorrow of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, cauſing him to grieue, that hee hath offended that man, vvho is ſo ready to ſuccour and to relieue his vvants and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries.</p>
            <p>To conclude this firſt point,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.14. Rom. 12.18.</note> 
               <hi>Seeke peace and enſue it, if it be poſſible: as much as in you is, haue peace with all men: For</hi> (as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith) <hi>hee which hateth his Brother is a murderer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Epiſt. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>and wee know no murderer hath eternall life abiding in him. But</hi> (as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>let vs loue one another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Epiſt. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>for loue commeth of God, and euery one which loueth, is borne of God, and knoweth God.</hi> And ſo I paſſe vnto the obiect whom wee muſt loue, namely, our Neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy Neighbour.] Difficile eſt humanam animam nihil amare:</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Hierome</hi>) It is hard that the Soule of man
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12337:13"/>
ſhould loue nothing: for, <hi>Nihili eſt qui nihil amat:</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plautus</hi>) Hee is to be eſteemed as nothing which loueth nothing, eſpecially ſeeing there are ſo many obiects for to loue. In which reſpect it is obſerued, that there is no one word in the Greeke tongue, which receiueth ſo many Compoſitions, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Loue.</hi> There is,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</item>
               </list>
that is,
<list>
                  <item>The drunkards loue.</item>
                  <item>The Leachers loue.</item>
                  <item>Ambitious loue.</item>
                  <item>Pleaſures loue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But of all other obiects of loue, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth reckon vp foure, as moſt principall,<note place="margin">De doct. Chriſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> ſaying; <hi>Quatuor ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> There are foure things eſpecially to be beloued: one which is aboue vs, (that is, God:) ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what wee are, (that is, our ſelues:) the third, which is neere vnto vs, (that is, our neighbour:) the fourth, vvhich is beneath vs, (that is, our bodies.) This preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion offereth to ſpeake onely of the third: and here one may aske with the Expounder of the Law,<note place="margin">Luke 18.29.</note> 
               <hi>Who is my neighbour?</hi> Indeede the Iewes in Chriſts time eſteemed none their neighbours but their friends: the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſort thinke them onely their neighbours who dwell neere vnto them:<note place="margin">In <hi>22.</hi> Mat.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> hee ſaith, By neighbour is vnderſtood
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12337:13"/>
Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe hee is the true Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, which poureth Oyle and Wine into our ſoares. But Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> moſt truely tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, <hi>Proximus hoc loco,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 52.</note> 
               <hi>non ſanguinis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquitate, ſed rationis ſocietate penſandus eſt, in qua ſocij ſunt omnes homines:</hi> Our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is not to be eſteemed him which is neereſt to vs in bloud, or in place, but hee which is our companion in reaſon: now eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man being a reaſonable Creature, euery man is therefore our neighbour.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Ser. <hi>59.</hi> de temp.</note> the ſame Father ſheweth three things, in which we are all neighbours: firſt, in that wee are all borne alike: ſecondly, in that wee all dye alike: thirdly, in that vvee all hope alike for the heauenly inheritance: And Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> giueth a moſt vvitty and pithy reaſon why euery man is our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,<note place="margin">In <hi>4.</hi> ad Epheſ.</note> be hee friend or foe, Chriſtian or Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, and that becauſe it is commaunded, <hi>Thou ſhalt not lye with thy neighbours Wife:</hi> now if <hi>Neighbour</hi> be onely Chriſtians and friends, then it were lawfull to lye, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adulterie with Turkes, Iewes, Infidels, and with our enemies; but this is moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: and therefore by conſequent, euery man is our neighbour. And thus hauing ſhewed you by <hi>Neighbour</hi> is vnderſtood euery particular man of what Country or condition ſoeuer, let mee now vrge among many, three ſpeciall arguments to moue
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12337:14"/>
vs, and to ſtirre vs vp to loue our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <p>The firſt reaſon enforcing loue (beſides the infinite places in Scripture commanding vs) is taken from neceſſitie:<note place="margin">1 Iohn 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that loueth not, knoweth not God, for God is Loue:</hi> ſo then as the body ſeuered from the ſoule, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a dead carkaſſe and a ſenſeleſſe truncke; ſo the ſoule vnited to the body, and yet voyde of loue, is dead, and ſenſeleſſe in ſpirituall things: for, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Hee which hateth his brother is a man-ſlayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>and wee know no murderer hath eternall life abiding in him.</hi> And indeede how can we loue Chriſt which is our head, and hate our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours which are his members.</p>
            <p>If a man ſhould ſtroake one on the head vvith his hand, ſpeake him faire vvith his tongue, and yet in the meane time, did beate and cut his body with a ſword, no man would thinke he loued that man: Euen ſo, how can wee loue Chriſt, which is our Head, and yet hate one another which are his Members? Wherefore let this teach vs,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 4.11.</note> that if GOD ſo loued vs, then ought wee to loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; now God ſo loued vs, as to dye for vs when wee were his enemies, then muſt wee loue one another, though vvee are enemies one to the other: for to requite good for good is the part of humanitie; to requite euill for euill, is the tricke of a beaſt; to repay euill
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12337:14"/>
for good, is the property of a Diuell; but to repay good for euill, to bleſſe him which curſeth thee, is the dutie of euery true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian whatſoeuer he be: <hi>For,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 13.35.</note> 
               <hi>by this ſhall all men know if yee be my Diſciples, if yee loue one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon mouing vs to loue, is taken from our Creation: Wee finde not in the Bible, that GOD made all the Angels of one Angell; or all the Fiſhes, of the great Whale; or all the Birds, of the ſurmounting Eagle; or all the Beaſts, of the huge Elephant; or all the Plants, of the tall Cedar: but vvee reade in the Scripture, that GOD made all mankinde of one and the ſame <hi>Adam,</hi> which teacheth vs thus much, ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De bono coniug. contra Ioum.</note> that wee ſhould all liue like brethren, and loue as one, becauſe we proceede from one. And <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith very well,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> if we all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from one man, whom God did make, then are wee all of conſanguinitie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a great ſinne to hate euen a wicked man. Looke alſo a little vnto our procreation and bringing forth into the world: the Trees haue height to reſiſt the violence of Beaſts, ſtrong Armes to wreſtle with the force of windes, Leaues to keepe from them the heate in Summer, and Barkes to defend the colde Froſts in Winter: among the Birds, the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle hath her claw, the Porcupine her quils, the Crane her bill, the Hawke his tallent:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12337:15"/>
among the Beaſts of the Forreſt, the Lyon hath his tayle, the Beare his paw, the Bull his horne, the Boare his tuske: among the Fiſhes of the Sea, the Sepia hath a miſt of Incke, the Crabbe his ſhell, the Polypus his change of colours: thus euery creature commeth forth with ſome defence for it ſelfe, with offence for it foe; onely man, poore miſerable man, commeth naked into the vvorld: whereby Nature her ſelfe the common parent of all, doth teach vs, that man of al creatures, ſhould be moſt louing and peaceable one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as hauing ſpeech giuen vnto him, which is denied to other Creatures, to make him more ſociable. Wherefore let there be that loue betweene man and man, as is betweene beaſt and beaſt. If one Sheepe be faint, the vvhole flocke will ſtand betweene it and the Sun vntill it be comforted. Among the Bees, <hi>aegrotante vna lamentantur omnes:</hi> If one Bee doe waxe faint, all the whole Hiue doth mourne. If a man will not be as kinde to man as Beaſts are among themſelues, yet let men be as kinde to men, as the beaſts are to men. Wee reade of thankfull Lyons, kinde Eagles, louing Dogs, Wolues haue nouriſhed ſome men, Beares haue ſuckled others: in the Scripture wee reade how <hi>Elias</hi> was fed by Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens:<note place="margin">2 Kings 17.6. Dan. 6.22. Luke 16.21. Actes 28.5.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel</hi> was ſafe in the middeſt of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Dogs did licke the ſoares of poore <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus:</hi> the Viper did not hurt S. <hi>Paul. O cum
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12337:15"/>
deteſtandam humanae malitiae crudelitatem! Aues paſcunt, Ferae parcunt, homines ſaeuiunt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> O the moſt deteſtable cruelty of mans malice! the Birds feede vs, the Beaſts doe ſpare vs, and yet one man is a Wolfe, yea, a Diuell to another: well yet let one man be as louing to another, as the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels are among themſelues, for they vvill ioyne together to the deſtruction of man, as vvee ſee by him vvho ſaid his name vvas Legion, becauſe vve are many;<note place="margin">Marke 9.</note> and ſo let vs loue together to deſtroy the Diuell.</p>
            <p>All men of one trade will alwayes ioyne together for the maintenance of their trade,<note place="margin">The Kings A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie for the oath.</note> ſo wee being all Chriſtians, hauing one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one Redeemer, one Sanctifier, one Mother the Church, partakers of one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, one Faith, and hoping for one king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in Heauen, muſt needes vnite our ſelues in hearty Loue and Chriſtian charitie thereby the better to ouercome the World, the Fleſh, and the Diuell.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon to ſtirre vs vp to loue our neighbour, is taken from nature; which teacheth the perfection of all things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in vnitie. Looke vpon the heauens, there is one motion of the Sunne, another of the Moone, another of the Starres, yet they are all carryed about <hi>motu primi mobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> by the motion of the firſt moueable: deſcend lower to the foure Elements, Fire,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12337:16"/>
Water, Ayre, Earth, vvhat more differing then their qualities hot and cold, moyſt and drye? yet all theſe agree together to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of one mixed body and ſolled ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: come to thoſe creatures which haue life and motion, as Plants, Hearbs, Trees. In the Tree there is the body, the Barke, the Bowes, the Leaues; all thoſe parts differ one from another, yet all haue their perfection from one and the ſelfe-ſame roote which is grounded in the earth.</p>
            <p>Looke vpon the Beaſtes and Fowles, no one Beaſt or Bird of the ſame kinde will hurt another: as the Hawke flyeth after the Partrich, not another Hawke; the bloud-Hound pulleth downe the Deere, not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hound, and ſo man ſhould not haue vvarre with man, but with the Deuill. Come vnto man the moſt excellent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in nature, and ſee how euery thing in him tendeth vnto vnitie: for his outward parts; the eye cannot ſay to the foote, I haue no neede of thee, but the eye guideth the foote, the foote beareth the eye, one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber receiueth into the body what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, another euacuateth and caſteth out of the body vvhat is ſuperfluous, yet all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for the good of the vvhole body. View the inward parts of man, how many ſeuerall Nerues and ſinewes are there in the body? yet all from one head the braine: how
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12337:16"/>
much blood diſperſed thorow ſeuerall veines, yet all from one fountaine the liuer; how many ſpirits and motions, yet all from the heart: from theſe three principall parts the Head, the Liuer, the Heart, are diffuſed into the vvhole man, Life, Sence, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet theſe three haue but one head, vvhich is the ſoule of man: and as Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy telleth vs, <hi>Anima eſt tota in toto &amp; tota in qualibet parte:</hi> The ſoule is alike whole in the vvhole body as in the little finger, and alike whole in the little finger as in the whole body: wherefore embrace loue, ſeeke peace,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> vvithout vvhich no man ſhall ſee GOD.</p>
            <p>Is then thy enemy greater then thou art? be quiet, <hi>&amp; tibi parce,</hi> ſpare thy ſelfe, meddle not with one that is mightier then thy ſelfe. The Toade may ſwel till he burſt, before he be ſo bigge as the Oxe. Is thy enemy leſſe then thy ſelfe? <hi>(impar congreſſus Achilli) parce ſibi,</hi> ſpare him, it is no glory for a man to beat a Boy; no credit for a great rich man to oppreſſe a poore meane man: the Lyon will ſeldome meddle with a vvoman, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with a little childe. Is thy enemy thine equal? <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth thee, that the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a man deferreth his anger,<note place="margin">Prou. 19.11.</note> and his glory is to paſſe by an offence. Thou wilt ſpend fiue pounds to make him ſpend ten, this is but to be the enuious man. It was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12337:17"/>
once granted that the enuious man, and the couetous man ſhould both haue their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, and hee which wiſhed laſt ſhould haue the firſt mans vviſh doubled; ſo they did much ſtriue vvho ſhould vviſh laſt, in the end it vvas graunted to the couetous man: heereupon the enuious man vviſhed one of his eyes to be put out; vvhich done, the couetous man hath both his put out, ſo then to ſpend twenty pounds to make thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſpend fortie, is to be but enuious, make the beſt of it. It is but like too boyes at boxes, the one getteth a blew face, the other a bloody noſe, but both of them are well bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. <hi>Aeſope</hi> telleth vs a fable how the Mouſe and the Frog would needes fight together, and in the middeſt of the battell came the Kite and deuoured them both: euen ſo take heed, while neighbors are at variance among themſelues, ſeeking to doe miſchiefe one to other, ſuddenly commeth death and taketh them all away, and vvhen they are thus dead in their hatred and malice, let the diuell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to torment them all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Serm. cap. <hi>168.</hi> de tempore.</note>To ſhut vp this point with S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his counſell, ſaying, Seeing euery man as hee is a man, is thy neighbour, but as hee is an euill man and offereth vvrong, he is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thy enemy but his owne foe, therefore loue in him his ſoule and his body, that is, loue thy neighbour whom God hath made,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12337:17"/>
but hate and deteſt his malice, and other ſinnes vvhich the Diuell hath by temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons worked into his ſoule, ſo ſhalt thou be like a wiſe Phiſition who loueth his patient, and hateth his diſeaſe. Thus much for the obiect, vvhom we muſt loue, our neighbor: let mee now ſpeake of the laſt thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, namely, how farre our loue muſt be extended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As thy ſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom. <hi>21.</hi> in Geneſi.</note>] As Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith very vvell, <hi>Neque vel ſillaba vel apiculus eſt in ſacris Scripturis in cuius profundo non ſit grandis quiſpiam theſaurus.</hi> There is not one ſillable or tittle in the holy Scripture, but ſearching thereof ſome great and hidden treaſure may be found; for if it be a true axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome in Philoſophie, <hi>Natura nihil facit fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra,</hi> that nature doth nothing in vaine, then it muſt be much more true of the God of nature, that he vvill ſpeake nothing in vaine, and that in his holy vvrit.</p>
            <p>This is partly ſeene in this vvord <hi>As,</hi> the vvhich hath foure ſeuerall ſignifications in the Bible.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it ſignifieth the likeneſſe of a thing but not the truth of a thing, as in Saint <hi>Matthew.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 26.55.</note> 
               <hi>Ye came out as againſt a thiefe with bils and with ſtaues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this word <hi>As</hi> ſignifieth the truth of a thing, but not the likeneſſe of a thing, in Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>Wee ſaw the glory of him
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12337:18"/>
as the glory of the onely begotten Sonne of the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it ſignifieth both the likeneſſe and the truth of a thing, as to the <hi>Hebrewes, God offereth himſelfe vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>as vnto chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, it ſignifieth <hi>rei qualitatem ſed non aequalitatem,</hi> the quality, but not the equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a thing,<note place="margin">Luke 6.36.</note> as in S. <hi>Luke, Be ye mercifull, as your Father is mercifull.</hi> Where the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, wee ſhould be as well mercifull as God, not as much, for that is impoſſible; and in this laſt ſignification is this word <hi>[As]</hi> taken in this place, <hi>Loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,</hi> that is, <hi>pari affectu, ſed non pari effectu,</hi> as the Schoole ſpeaketh;<note place="margin">3. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 29.</note> ſo the meaning is, that we muſt loue our neighbour as well as our ſelues, but not as much as our ſelues; for there are degrees in loue, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Do good vnto all men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>but eſpecially to the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith:</hi> and among Chriſtians, as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> obſerueth,<note place="margin">In Ezech. 44.</note> after God vve muſt loue our Father, and our Mother, our Children, our Brothers and Siſters, our Kinſefolkes, our owne houſehold, <hi>for hee is worſe then an infidell which will not prouide for his familie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> and therefore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith very well, <hi>Omnes homines aeque diligendi ſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de doct. Chriſt. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> All men are alike vvell to be beloued, but vvhen a man cannot doe good to all, then hee muſt eſpecially helpe thoſe, which are neereſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12337:18"/>
him in place, in time, or by ſome other occaſions, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hauing now ſet down the ſence and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the words, that wee muſt loue our neighbour as well as our ſelues; let vs now ſhew how vvell wee muſt loue all men; and this firſt in generall, then in particular. For the generall, vvhat the Law of nature ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the negatiue, <hi>Quod tibi non vis fieri, alteri ne feceris:</hi> What ye will not haue done to you, doe not vnto others, that ſame the Law of the Goſpell ſpeaketh affirmatiuely, as yee would others ſhould doe vnto you, ſo doe yee vnto them; for this is the Law and the Prophets. Now then examine thy ſelfe by this rule: Suppoſe thou wert poore and needy, and driuen to begge thy bread from houſe to houſe, when thou diddeſt aske an almes, wouldeſt not thou be glad to receiue it? vvould it not grieue thee to be ſent away empty without meat for thy belly, or cloaths for thy backe, or harbour for the vveather? ſurely thy conſcience will tell thee yes, vvhy then, as you would another ſhould doe to thee, ſo do thou vnto him; relieue the poore, viſit the ſicke, comfort the fatherleſſe, &amp;c. Againe, if thy enemie had thee at aduantage, vvouldeſt thou be contented that he ſhould take away thy goods, thy good name, that he ſhould beat thee, hurt thee, kil thee, or the like, examine thy conſcience, it will tell thee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12337:19"/>
no: why then, as thou wouldeſt another ſhould doe vnto thee, ſo doe thou vnto him. Forgiue thine enemy, make him not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume his goods, robbe him not of his good name, do not ſtrike him, hurt him, kil him, or the like. And as in theſe, ſo in all other things examine thy ſelfe, &amp; when thou goeſt about any thing concerning any man, remember this ſhort leſſon, <hi>Doe as thou wouldeſt be done vnto,</hi> and it will keepe thee from many ſins: for aſſure thy ſelfe, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, thou doſt not loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">De monit. Eccle. Catho.</note> if thou doſt not ſtriue to bring him to that good, which thou deſireſt to enioy thy ſelfe. And this for the generall.</p>
            <p>Giue me now leaue more particularly to ſhew how we ſhould loue our neighbour, by a few ſimilitudes drawne from the naturall body of man, and the members therof. Firſt, one member in the naturall body doth not enuy another: euen ſo, we muſt not enuy at our neighbours proſperitie. This ſin of Enuy is of all other moſt fooliſh; for the couetous man hath a little wealth for his ſoule, the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous man hath a little pleaſure for his ſoule, the ambitious man hath a little honor for his ſoule, but the enuious man giueth away his ſoule to the Diuell for nothing, hauing onely hearts griefe and miſery: yet many men in theſe dayes are like <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey,</hi> of which one could not abide his ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12337:19"/>
the other could not endure his equall: but this ſhould not be among Chriſtians. For why ſhould my eye be euill becauſe Gods eye is good? Wherefore as in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, if one member ſuffer,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.26.</note> all the members will ſuffer with it; as if the foote be hurt, the eye will looke to it, the hand will reach for it, the tongue will ſpeake for it, &amp;c. Euen ſo muſt wee take compaſſion of one anothers miſeries, like <hi>Scipio Africanus Minor,</hi> who (as <hi>Appian</hi> reporteth) did weepe when hee ſaw Carthage burne, ſaying that Rome, his mother Citie, might one day burne ſo: Euen ſo, wee eyther are in miſery like our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or wee haue beene in ſuch miſery, or before wee dye, wee may be as wretched as our neighbour; therefore let vs haue a Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy and fellow-feeling of each others ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity. Againe, if one member reioyce, all the other members reioyce with it: ſo muſt wee be glad at others good; for this is to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall,<note place="margin">Luke 15.10.</note> the Angels in heauen reioyce at the conuerſion of a ſinner vpon earth. What <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> ſaith to his friend, that euery Chriſtian muſt from his heart ſpeake vnto his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>Mihi id expedit quod tibi, aut non ſum amicus, niſi quicquid agitur ad te pertinens me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt:</hi> Looke what is good for thee, that I eſteeme good for mee, and ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, otherwiſe I am not thy true Chriſtian neighbour and friend.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12337:20"/>Secondly, one member in the body doth not appropriate its good vnto it ſelfe, but to the whole body: as the eye ſeeth not for it ſelfe, but for the whole body, and ſo of the reſt: Euen ſo, wee being all members of one myſticall Body, whoſe Head is Chriſt, muſt communicate to the good and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties one of another. Wherefore Loue muſt be to our actions, as our hand is to our body; the hand it clotheth the backe, it feedeth the belly, and doth all other neceſſary offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the body: Euen ſo loue muſt practiſe all good actions to the members of Chriſts Myſticall Body, in feeding the hungry, in clothing the naked, and the like. And as the hand couereth the ſoares in the body by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of plaiſters, ſo Loue muſt couer the multitude of offences, which our fellow-members commit, by forgetting and forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them. For as the hand is not all one lumpe of fleſh, but diuided into ſeuerall ioynts and fingers, whereby it is more fit to performe its dutie: euen ſo are we by Gods ſpeciall prouidence, diuided into ſeuerall members, that wee may the better performe the workes of loue, not like a Boare in a ſtye, to liue vnto our ſelues: nor like a Dogge in a kennell to barke at all that goe by, but to let all our actions be done in loue, doing to all others, as we would all others ſhould doe vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:12337:20"/>Thirdly, one member in the body hurt by another, doth not reuenge it ſelfe, as if the hand let fall a ſtone or waight vpon the foot, the foote doth not kicke and ſpurne at the hand againe, but beareth it patiently: Euen ſo muſt wee beare and put vp wrongs one of another, referring all to GOD, who in his due time will reuenge;<note place="margin">De vero cultu. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non minus mali eſt referre, quam inferre iniuriam:</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>) It is no leſſe euill to requite a wrong, then to offer a wrong: for hee which reuengeth wrong, doth imitate him of whom hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued iniurie; now in that he imitateth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that which is bad, hee can by no meanes himſelfe proue good.<note place="margin">Serm. de Ira.</note> Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth further, affirming that hee which reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth wrong, is worſe then hee which begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth wrong: for that which another man of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vnto thee is good or bad; if good, why then art thou angry with him? I, but it vvas bad: is it ſo? why then doſt thou ſeeke to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and requite that to thy neighbour, which thine owne conſcience telleth thee is bad, and vvhich thou thy ſelfe condemneſt for ſinne in thy brother? If a man ſee his enemy ſicke of the Plague ſoares, will he to reuenge himſelfe of his enemy, ſtriue to haue the plague in his body alſo? euery one will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme ſuch a man a mad man, or a foole. Are we then wiſe for our bodies, and fooliſh for our ſoules? He beloued which offereth thee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12337:21"/>
iniurie, hath filled his ſoule with ſinne, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as without Gods grace, and his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, hee cannot be ſaued: now then for thee to ſeeke to repay this wrong, is to fill thy ſoule likewiſe with ſinne, and to make it abhominable in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>This then condemneth moſt ſpecially our priuate duels vpon euery ſmall punctilio of Honour to challenge the field: conſider with thy ſelfe in reaſon (ſetting Gods Word aſide) are we not all, in the Kingdome, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body politicke, the King being the Head? now hee which dareth fight with the Kings friend, dareth fight with the Kings enemie: then what vvrong is here to the whole Kingdome, for a priuate wrong offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto me, I ſhall bereaue my country of him which in the front of an Army may kill a Generall, and ſo by that meanes may ſaue the life and liberty of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?<note place="margin">Exod. 23.5.</note> In Gods Law it is written, <hi>if thy enemies beaſt doe fall into a ditch, thou ſhalt helpe him out.</hi> Is ſo great loue to be ſhewed to my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Beaſt? O how much then ought I to loue the perſon of mine enemie, who is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after Gods owne Image, and for whom CHRIST IESVS dyed and ſhed his precious bloud?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the honourable members in the body doe not deſpiſe the meaner, nor can they; for the head cannot ſay to the foote, I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12337:21"/>
haue no neede of thee: Euen ſo, great men muſt not deſpiſe meane men, neyther can we liue without one another. See how God doth not giue to euery nation euery commoditie, becauſe men ſhould traffique one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and diſtance of place and language ſhould not ſeparate our loue. See likewiſe in euery nation how euery man hath not euery Art, ſome are Taylors, ſome Maſons, ſome Husbandmen, ſome Merchants, and this to teach vs loue, becauſe wee all ſtand in need one of another. It is noted as a great plague in Iſraell,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.19.</note> that there was not one Smith left among them; this ſeemeth but a baſe Trade, yet ſo neceſſary a member to the body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke, as the Common-wealth cannot ſtand without it. The Lyon entangeld in nets had neede of the little Mouſe to gnaw the threds in ſunder before hee could get looſe: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not the greateſt and richeſt men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the poore and meane men, for they ſtand in neede of the meaneſt, if for nothing elſe, yet to pray for them.</p>
            <p>It is well noted by <hi>Primaſius,</hi> that the rich man is like the Elme-tree, the poore man is like the Vine-tree: the Elme vnder-proppeth the Vine, and ſo cauſeth it to ſtand and beare fruit, which otherwiſe would fall and wither; the Vine againe ouer-ſhadoweth the Elme, and cauſeth it to be greene and flouriſhing, vvhich otherwiſe would periſh and decay:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12337:22"/>
Euen ſo, the rich men by their almes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the poore, who otherwiſe would ſtarue, and the poore men againe ouer-ſhadow the rich men with their prayers to God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they doe the better flouriſh in this world, and liue for euer in the world to come. See this to be verified in rich <hi>Oneſephorus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.16.</note> who relieued poore <hi>Paul</hi> in priſon; and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> againe deſired God to be mercifull to <hi>Oneſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus;</hi> there is a bleſſing in this life: and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he prayed, God grant hee may finde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in that day; there is a prayer for the life to come.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, one member in the body doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger it ſelfe for another; as let one ſtrike at the head with a naked ſword, and the hand will aduenture cutting off to defend the head: Euen ſo muſt wee runne into danger for the good one of another, and moſt eſpecially we muſt die for our head, if occaſion ſerue, becauſe before our head hath dyed for vs. To giue of our abundance to the poore is pleaſing vnto Almightie God, but to ſpare out of our owne neceſſities is farre more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God, as wee ſee the poore Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes mite was of greater value in the ſight of GOD,<note place="margin">Luke 11.3.4.</note> then the greater gifts of richer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: ſo at all times to helpe one another is charitable, but to helpe others vvith ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of our ſelues, and vvith preiudice of our owne eſtates, is farre more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12337:22"/>
to GOD, and pleaſing vnto man.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, one member in the body recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not anothers foode, but ſendeth it to the other parts of the body: ſo the rich man muſt not eate vp the poore man, but rather he muſt communicate to his neceſſities, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt the poore man ſteale from the rich, but follow rather his labour, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon Gods prouidence: for neceſſary it is for a good ſtomacke to haue hunger and appetite vnto meate, which ariſeth of wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tery humours which doe gnaw vpon the ſplene: ſecondly, the ſtomacke muſt haue iudgement and diſcretion to chuſe ſuch meate, which doth beſt agree with the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, and refuſe the contrary, which iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ariſeth of foure muſcles comming from the Head: thirdly, there muſt be ſtrength and vigor to be able to digeſt the meate which it receiueth, leaſt otherwiſe it turne into raw crudities, and ſo breede diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the body; which heate and vigour ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of motions and ſpirits which are ſent from the heart: all theſe are neceſſary, yet none ſufficient, vnleſſe there be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſperſion of the foode, to ſend the nouriſhment to the other parts of the body, which is done by the bloud thorow the veines. In like manner neceſſary it is, for a Chriſtian man to haue faith,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> for <hi>without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> In like manner ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12337:23"/>
it is for a chriſtian man to giue almes, and to pray to God, to be patient in aduerſity, &amp;c. but our faith profiteth nothing vnleſſe it worketh by Loue; neyther is any other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue acceptable in the ſight of GOD vnleſſe it be begunne, continued, and ended in Loue, therefore the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> 
               <hi>If I haue all things and yet want loue, it profiteth mee nothing:</hi> the hand can reach and receiue a gift of it ſelfe, but the hand cannot cut any thing of it ſelfe without a knife, or ſome ſuch like inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; euen ſo, Faith, as the hand of the ſoule, is able to aſcend vp to Chriſts croſſe, and to apply his merits vnto the ſoule, but faith can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not of it ſelfe bring forth the workes of the firſt and ſecond Table, yet, as if you put a knife into the hand, the hand vvill cut, ſo ioyne Loue to Faith, and then faith working by Loue, doth performe all thoſe Chriſtian duties which GOD requireth of vs in his Law.</p>
            <p>Hence a Chriſtian man is not vnfitly compared to a Conduit: to vvhich there is a Spring, vvhence the Water floweth: a Leaden Pipe, through vvhich the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is conueyed: a Cyſterne, to receiue the Water: and a Cocke, to open and let forth Water to all which ſtand in neede. So eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian is as a Conduit; the Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head from whence the Waters of Life doe flow, is IESVS CHRIST; the Leaden
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12337:23"/>
Pipe whereby theſe liuing Waters are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayed, is a true and a liuely Faith: the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne vvhich doth receiue theſe Waters, is the Soule of man: now Loue muſt be as the Cocke, to open, and bring forth all deedes of mercy to all thoſe which ſtand in neede.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, one member in the body doth tremble to be cut and ſeuered from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo ſhould vvee feare and tremble to be ſeparated one from another by hatred and diſſention. The ſoule giueth life vnto the body, and to euery member of the body, yet not vnleſſe they be vnited and ioyned to the body: for cut off the hand or the foote, and then the Soule ceaſeth to giue life to them, but preſently they dye. So Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD giueth life vnto the Soule of euery man, but not vnleſſe vvee be vnited and ioyned one to another in loue and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: <hi>For hee which loueth not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>knoweth not God, for God is Loue; but if wee loue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, God dwelleth in vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 12.</note> 
               <hi>and his loue is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in vs:</hi> So that hee vvhich liueth in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and diſſention, ſeeking reuenge, is a meere Atheiſt, no true Chriſtian: for, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any man ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 20.</note> 
               <hi>I loue God, and hate his Brother, hee is a lyar.</hi> And S. <hi>Gregory, If they ſhall be the Children of God which are peace-makers, then ſurely they are the Children of the Diuell, which are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12337:24"/>
peace-breakers.</hi> Therefore euery Chriſtian man muſt be like vnto a Maſon, vvhich hath two hands, vvith the one hee hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth faſt on the Ladder, to keepe himſelfe from falling, vvith the other hee reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out Tyle and Morter to his fellow la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers: Euen ſo, in building Gods Church and houſe, euery one muſt haue two hands; the one the hand of Faith, vvhereby hee himſelfe may climbe vp to the Croſſe of CHRIST, and ſo be ſaued from falling into the pit of Hell; the other muſt be the hand of Loue, to reach forth deedes of mercy and of Chriſtian affection to our Fellovv-labourers and Builders of Gods houſe.</p>
            <p>To draw to a concluſion: the loue of men, in this age, is like vnto a Tree, but it is the Figge-tree CHRIST curſed in the Goſpell, vvhich brought forth Leaues and no fruit: ſo vvee are louing in ſhew, not in deede, vvhereas our loue ſhould be like vnto a Tree vvhich is rooted deepe in the earth, and beareth branches vpward, and fruit vvhich hangeth downeward, ſo our Loue muſt be rooted in Humilitie: he vvhich vvill runne vp a high ſteepy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, muſt goe ſtooping, not bolt vpright. Heauen is a high hill, he which vvill runne thither muſt haue no high aſpiring thoughts but be humble.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12337:24"/>Obſerue among all the beatitudes which our Sauiour reckoneth vp, hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the hungry, for they ſhall be ſatisfied: bleſſed are the meeke, for they ſhall inherit the earth:</hi> but <hi>bleſſed are the poore in ſpirit,</hi> that is, the humble minded man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for theirs,</hi> already, <hi>is the kingdome of Heauen.</hi> Againe, our Loue muſt beare branches vpward, to loue God aboue all, that though the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers of Aegypt made many Serpents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 7.12.</note> yet the Serpent of <hi>Moſes</hi> did deuoure them all: ſo though mans loue haue many obiects, yet the loue of GOD muſt ouer-come them all. Laſtly, our Loue muſt bring forth fruit hanging downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to our neighbour as our ſelues, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quem potuerit hominem</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine) vel beneficentiae conſolatione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 52.</note> 
               <hi>vel doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae informatione, vel diſciplinae coer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ione ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat ad colendum Deum:</hi> That in as much as vvee can, wee ſhould bring euery man to worſhip GOD, eyther by comforting him vvith deedes of mercy in his diſtreſſe, or by inſtructing him in knowledge if hee be ignorant, or by curbing him with the rod of correction when he is faulty.</p>
            <p>The loue of men in this age is like vnto fire, whoſe nature is to conſume all that it layeth hold on: ſo wee ſtriue to eate vp one another, by coſening, by Vſury, by Symony,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12337:25"/>
and Briberie, vvhereas indeede our loue ſhould be like vnto fire. Firſt, the nature of fire is to aſcend; ſo our loue muſt aſcend vpward to loue GOD aboue all, our Loue muſt (<hi>de Deo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de ſub. ſtat. amoris.</note> 
               <hi>cum Deo, ad Deum currere,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) runne from God, as being grounded in him; vvith God, as being obedient vnto his Lawes; vnto God, as reſting in him alone. Secondly, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of fire is to ſhine, and to giue light; ſo the light of our loue muſt ſo ſhine before others,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.16.</note> that they ſeeing our good vvorkes, may learne to glorifie our Father which is in Heauen. Wee muſt euery one be like <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> vvho was <hi>(Lucerna ardens &amp; lucens)</hi> a burning and a ſhining Lampe in Gods Church. Thirdly, the nature of fire is not to giue heate to one or two, but to all that come neere vnto it: ſo our loue muſt not extend it ſelfe onely to our ſelues, and to our Children, but to all the members of Chriſt Ieſus; yea, to all mankinde; be hee a good man, nay be hee a bad man he muſt be relieued. <hi>Charitas non iudicat de meritis, ſed de miſerijs:</hi> Charitie doth not iudge of our brothers merits, but of his miſeries. And then remember when thou denieſt loue to one which is wicked, that <hi>if God were extreame to marke what is done amiſſe O Lord who might abide it?</hi> Fourthly, the nature of fire is neuer to goe out, if there
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12337:25"/>
be Coale or Wood, or matter to burne: euen ſo, our Loue ſhould neuer be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of vvell doing, neuer vveary of forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. <hi>Muſculus</hi> ſaith very well, <hi>Vt nequit mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerecordiae praeſcribi modus, ita nec operum certus numerus:</hi> As none can preſcribe a meane how farre mercy ſhould be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo no man can ſet downe a finite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how many vvorkes of mercy are to be performed: for, as the miſeries of man are infinite, ſo the vvorkes of loue muſt be infinite. Now, a man is ſicke, and ſo needeth reliefe: anone, hee breaketh his legge, then hee is in vvant againe: now, his Houſe is burnt; and ſo <hi>in infinitum;</hi> our life being a Sea of Glaſſe, as tumultuous as the ſea, as brittle as glaſſe.</p>
            <p>The loue of men in theſe dayes is like to the Sunne, whoſe nature is to diſpell dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and lay all things open to euery mans view; ſo our loue is like the Sunne in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſing and talking of our neighbours faults and infirmities, like vnto Flyes in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, which if there be but one galled piece on the horſe backe, they will be lick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, and let the ſound fleſh alone; ſo the conditions of vs in this age is to be tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and taxing our brothers faults, neuer commending his vertues: but hearken what our Sauiour ſaith; <hi>Hipocrite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.5.</note> 
               <hi>firſt plucke the beame out of thine owne eye, and then looke
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12337:26"/>
into the moate which is in thy brother eye:</hi> hee which is without ſinne himſelfe, let him be cenſuring his brothers ſinne: hee is a foole which hath his owne houſe on fire, and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it burne and ſo runne to looke vpon the fire on his neighbours houſe: euen ſo, hee is vnwiſe which doth not clenſe his owne ſoule from ſinne, but is eſpying faults in his Brothers life. Others there are, which will not openly diſcloſe their neighbours infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, but as the Sunne ſhineth through a little creuiſſe and ſmall grate, ſo they will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly carry newes and tales of all they ſee and heare, and theſe are the fire-brands of much diſſention:<note place="margin">Prou. 26.20.</note> for <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way wood, the fire goeth out, ſo take away a tale-bearer, and contention ceaſeth:</hi> and indeede it is as great a ſinne to heare, as to tell tales: and there would neuer be one tongue in the head to tell tales, if there were not two eares on the out-ſide of the head to heare tales.</p>
            <p>But indeede our loue ſhould be like vnto the Sunne in his Circle, <hi>ſurſum, deo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſum, dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trorſum, ſiniſtrorſum:</hi> the Sunne in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ariſeth, ſo our loue muſt goe vpwards, we muſt loue our Superiours, and not enuy them: the Sunne at euening goeth downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſo our loue muſt deſcend, wee muſt loue our inferiours, and not deſpiſe them: the Sunne ſhineth on the right hand, ſo vvee muſt loue our friends, and not offend them:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12337:26"/>
the Sunne ſhineth on the left hand, ſo vvee muſt loue our enemies, and pray to God for them.</p>
            <p>Briefely to ſhut vp all, ſeeing (my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) that the wayes of God are the wayes of peace:<note place="margin">Prou. 3.</note> ſeeing it is a good and pleaſant thing for brethren to liue together in vnitie:<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> ſeeing Loue is the Chriſtian mans bagde, whereby hee muſt be knowne;<note place="margin">Iohn 13.35.</note> 
               <hi>By this ſhall all men know if yee be my Diſciples, if yee loue one another:</hi> ſeeing <hi>Bleſſed are the peace-makers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.9.</note> 
               <hi>for they ſhall be called the Children of God:</hi> ſeeing the Apoſtles in their Epiſtles, wiſh to them to whom they write, <hi>Grace and Peace from God the Father, and our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> ſeeing the Angels at the birth of Chriſt did ſing this Song, <hi>Glory be to God on high,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>peace on earth, good will towards men:</hi> ſeeing our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour willed his Diſciples, into what houſe they entred, to ſay; <hi>Peace be vnto this houſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 10.5.</note> ſeeing Chriſt Ieſus dyed to make peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and man: ſeeing at his death the laſt Legacie he bequeathed vnto his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples was Peace, <hi>My peace I giue vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 14.27.</note> 
               <hi>my peace I leaue among you:</hi> the firſt bleſſing after his Reſurrection, he deſired God to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon them, was Peace,<note place="margin">Iohn 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>Peace be vnto you:</hi> ſeeing the God whom wee ſerue is <hi>the God of peace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33.</note> let vs therefore labour and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to be in loue and charitie with all men, to ſeeke peace and follow after it, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12337:27"/>
as freely to forgiue others their treſpaſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, as wee deſire God to forgiue vs our treſpaſſes againſt him. And as the Toade be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee drinketh, doth caſt vp all his poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo let vs, before wee preſume to taſte of the heauenly foode of Gods Word, diſgorge all rancour and malice, leaſt otherwiſe God eſpying vs without our Wedding-Garment of Charitie,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.11.</note> bid that wee be taken and bound hand and foote, and caſt into vtter darkneſſe, where is nothing but weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 2.1.</note>Wherefore with S. <hi>Paul, I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, if there be any conſolation in Chriſt;</hi> in you, <hi>any comfort of loue, any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, any compaſſion or mercy; be yee like min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, hauing the ſame loue, being of one accord, and of one iudgement, that nothing be done through contention and vaine glory:</hi> but as in the Trinitie three perſons make but one God; as in Chriſt Ieſus two natures, his God-head and his man-hood, make but one perſon; as in the Sunne are many beames, yet but one light; as many graines of corne make but one loafe of bread; as many grapes make but one cup of wine: ſo wee, though wee are many and diuers, yet being ioyned together in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty loue, wee may make but one Church, and one body, whoſe head is Chriſt Ieſus in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and thus being lincked together in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charitie, wee may all of vs, from the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12337:27"/>
higheſt to the loweſt, from the richeſt to the pooreſt, from the eldeſt to the youngeſt, with one voyce, with one heart, and with one conſent, ſing forth and ſet forth the prayſes of God the Father, of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: To God the Father to God the Sonne, to God the holy Ghoſt, three Perſons in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, but one true and euer-liuing God in eſſence and in vnitie, be aſcribed and giuen, as is due, all honour, and glory, and power, from this time forth, for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 CORINTH. 13.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Finally, brethren fare yee well, be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one minde, liue in peace, and the God of loue and peace ſhall be with you.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
